CHAPTER V

While below they took me into the patio, that quiet inner garden which was so attractive from above. It was a lovely place. The moon was riding high and shone down into it; a slender fountain spray rose shimmering from its carved basin; on the southern-facing wall a great wistaria vine drooped in budding purple, and beds of violets made the air rich with soft fragrance.

Here and there were people walking; and in the shadowy corners sat young couples, apparently quite happy.

‚ÄúI suppose you don‚Äôt know the names of one of them,‚Äù I suggested.

‚ÄúOn the contrary, I know nearly all,‚Äù answered Hallie. ‚ÄúThese apartments are taken very largely by friends and acquaintances. You see, the gardens and roofs are in common, and there are the reading-rooms, ballrooms, and so on. It is pleasanter to be friends to begin with, and most of us get to be afterward, if we are not at first.

‚ÄúBut surely there are some disagreeable people left on earth!‚Äù

‚ÄúYes; but where there is so much more social life people get together in congenial sets,‚Äù put in Nellie; ‚Äújust as we used to in summer resorts.‚Äù

‚ÄúThere aren‚Äôt so many bores and fools as there used to be, John,‚Äù Owen remarked. ‚ÄúWe really do raise better people. Even the old ones have improved. You see, life is so much pleasanter and more interesting.‚Äù

‚ÄúWe‚Äôre all healthier. Uncle John, because we‚Äôre better fed; that makes us more agreeable.‚Äù

‚ÄúThere‚Äôs more art in the world to make us happier,‚Äù said Jerrold. ‚ÄúHallie thinks it‚Äôs all due to her everlasting bread and butter. Listen to that now!‚Äù

From a balcony up there in the moonlight came a delicious burst of melody; a guitar and two voices, and the refrain was taken up from another window, from one corner of the garden, from the roof; all in smooth accord.

‚ÄúYour group here must be an operatic one,‚Äù I suggested. But my nephew answered that it was not, but that music‚ÅÝ‚Äîgood music‚ÅÝ‚Äîwas so common now, and so well taught, that the average was high in both taste and execution.

We sat late that night, my new family bubbling over with things to say, and filling my mind with a confused sense of new advantages, unexplained and only half believed.

I could not bring myself to accept as commonplace facts the unusual excellences so glibly described, and I suppose my silence showed this as well as what I said, for my sister presently intervened with decision:

‚ÄúWe must all stop this for to-night,‚Äù she said. ‚ÄúJohn feels as if he was being forcibly fed‚ÅÝ‚Äîhe‚Äôs got to rest. Then I suggest that to-morrow Owen take him in hand‚ÅÝ‚Äîgo off for a tramp, why don‚Äôt you?‚ÅÝ‚Äîand really straighten out things. You see, there are two distinct movements to consider, the unconscious progress that would have taken place anyway in thirty years, and then the deliberate measures adopted by the ‚ÄòNew Lifers,‚Äô and it‚Äôs rather confusing. I‚Äôve labored with him all the way home now; I think the man‚Äôs point of view will help.‚Äù

* * * * *

Owen was a big man with a strong, wholesome face, and a quizzical little smile of his own. He and I went up the river next morning in a swift motor boat, which did not batter the still air with muffled banging as they used to do, and strolled off in the bright spring sunshine into Palisade Park.

‚ÄúWe‚Äôve saved all the loveliest of it‚ÅÝ‚Äîfor keeps,‚Äù he said. ‚ÄúOut here, where the grass and trees are just as they used to be, you won‚Äôt be bothered, and one expositor will be easier to handle than four at once. Now, shall I talk, or will you ask questions?‚Äù

‚ÄúI‚Äôd like to ask a few questions first, then you can expound by the hour. Do give me the long and short of this ‚Äòwomen-waked-up‚Äô proposition. What does it mean‚ÅÝ‚Äîto a man?‚Äù

Owen stroked his chin.

‚ÄúNo loss,‚Äù he said at length; ‚Äúat least, no loss that‚Äôs not covered by a greater gain. Do you remember the new biological theory in regard to the relative position of the sexes that was beginning to make headway when we were young?‚Äù

I nodded. ‚ÄúWard‚Äôs theory? Oh, yes; I heard something of it. Pretty far-fetched, it seemed to me.‚Äù

‚ÄúFar-fetched and dear-bought, but true for all that. You‚Äôll have to swallow it. The female is the race type; the male is her assistant. It‚Äôs established beyond peradventure.‚Äù

I meditated, painfully. I looked at Owen. He had just as happy and proud a look as if he was a real man‚ÅÝ‚Äînot merely an Assistant. I though of Jerrold‚ÅÝ‚Äînothing cowed about him; of the officers and men on the ship; of such men as I had seen in the street.

‚ÄúI suppose this applies in the main to remote origins?‚Äù I suggested.

‚ÄúIt holds good all through life‚ÅÝ‚Äîis just as true as it ever was.‚Äù

‚ÄúThen‚ÅÝ‚Äîdo you mean that women run everything, and men are only helpers?‚Äù

‚ÄúOh, no; I wasn‚Äôt talking about human life at all‚ÅÝ‚Äîonly about sex. ‚ÄòRunning things‚Äô has nothing to do with that. Women run some businesses and are in practically all, but men still do the bulk of the world‚Äôs work. There is a natural division of labor, after all.‚Äù

This was pleasant to hear, but he dashed my hopes.

‚ÄúMen do almost all the violent plain work‚ÅÝ‚Äîdigging and hewing and hammering; women, as a class, prefer the administrative and constructive kinds. But all that is open yet, and settling itself gradually; men and women are working everywhere. The big change which Nellie is always referring to means simply that women ‚Äòwaked up‚Äô to a realization of the fact that they were human beings.‚Äù

‚ÄúWhat were they before, pray?‚Äù

‚ÄúOnly female beings.‚Äù

‚ÄúFemale human beings, of course,‚Äù said I.

‚ÄúYes; a little human, but mostly female. Now they are mostly human. It is a great change.‚Äù

‚ÄúI don‚Äôt follow you. Aren‚Äôt they still wives and mothers?‚Äù

‚ÄúThey are still mothers‚ÅÝ‚Äîfar more so than they were before, as a matter of fact; but as to being wives‚ÅÝ‚Äîthere‚Äôs a difference.‚Äù

I was displeased, and showed it.

‚ÄúWell, is it Polygamy, or Polyandry, or Trial Marriages, or what?‚Äù

Owen gazed at me with an expression very like Nellie‚Äôs.

‚ÄúThere it is,‚Äù he said. ‚ÄúYou can only think about women in some sort of relation to men, of a change in marriage relations as merely a change in kind; whereas what has happened is a change in degree. We still have monogamous marriages, on a much purer and more lasting plane than a generation ago; but the word ‚Äòwife‚Äô does not mean what it used to.‚Äù

‚ÄúGo on‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI can‚Äôt follow you at all.‚Äù

‚ÄúA ‚Äòwife‚Äô used to be a possession; ‚Äòwilt thou be mine?‚Äô said the lover, and the wife was ‚Äòhis.‚Äô‚Ää‚Äù

‚ÄúWell‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhose else is she now?‚Äù I asked with some sharpness.

‚ÄúShe does not ‚Äòbelong‚Äô to anyone in that old sense. She is the wife of her husband in that she is his true lover, and that their marriage is legally recorded; but her life and work does not belong to him. He has no right to her ‚Äòservices‚Äô any more. A woman who is in a business‚ÅÝ‚Äîlike Hallie, for instance‚ÅÝ‚Äîdoes not give it up when she marries.‚Äù

I stopped him. ‚ÄúWhat! Isn‚Äôt Hallie married?‚Äù

‚ÄúNo‚ÅÝ‚Äînot yet.‚Äù

‚ÄúBut‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat is her flat?‚Äù

‚ÄúYes; why not?‚Äù He laughed at me. ‚ÄúYou see, you can‚Äôt imagine a woman having a home of her own. Hallie is twenty-three. She won‚Äôt marry for some years, probably; but she has her position and is doing excellent work. It‚Äôs only a minor inspectorship, but she likes it. Why shouldn‚Äôt she have a home?‚Äù

‚ÄúWhy doesn‚Äôt she have it with you?‚Äù

‚ÄúBecause I like to live with my wife. Her business, and mine, are in Michigan; Hallie‚Äôs in New York.‚Äù

‚ÄúAnd when she marries she keeps on being an inspector?‚Äù I queried.

‚ÄúPrecisely. The man who marries that young woman will have much happiness, but he will not ‚Äòown‚Äô her, and she will not be his wife in the sense of a servant. She will not darn his socks or cook his meals. Why should she?‚Äù

‚ÄúWill she not nurse his babies?‚Äù

‚ÄúNo; she will nurse her babies‚ÅÝ‚Äîtheir babies, not ‚Äòhis‚Äô merely.‚Äù

‚ÄúAnd keep on being an inspector?‚Äù

‚ÄúAnd keep on being an inspector‚ÅÝ‚Äîfor four hours a day‚ÅÝ‚Äîin two shifts. Not a bit more difficult than cooking, my dear boy.‚Äù

‚ÄúBut‚ÅÝ‚Äîshe will not be with her children‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúShe will be with her children twenty hours out of the twenty-four‚ÅÝ‚Äîif she wants to. But Hallie‚Äôs not specially good with children.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ You see, John, the women have specialized‚ÅÝ‚Äîeven in motherhood.‚Äù

Then he went on at considerable length to show how there had arisen a recognition of far more efficient motherhood than was being given; that those women best fitted for the work had given eager, devoted lives to it and built up a new science of Humaniculture; that no woman was allowed to care for her children without proof of capacity.

‚ÄúAllowed by whom?‚Äù I put in.

‚ÄúBy the other women‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe Department of Child Culture‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe Government.‚Äù

‚ÄúAnd the fathers‚ÅÝ‚Äîdo they submit to this, tamely?‚Äù

‚ÄúNo; they cheerfully agree and approve. Absolutely the biggest thing that has happened, some of us think, is that new recognition of the importance of childhood. We are raising better people now.‚Äù

I was silent for a while, pulling up bits of grass and snapping small sticks into inch pieces.

‚ÄúThere was a good deal of talk about Eugenics, I remember,‚Äù I said at last, ‚Äúand‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhat was that thing? Endowment of Motherhood?‚Äù

‚ÄúYes‚ÅÝ‚Äîman‚Äôs talk,‚Äù Owen explained. ‚ÄúYou see, John, we couldn‚Äôt look at women but in one way‚ÅÝ‚Äîin the old days; it was all a question of sex with us‚ÅÝ‚Äîinevitably, we being males. Our whole idea of improvement was in better breeding; our whole idea of motherhood was in each woman‚Äôs devoting her whole life to her own children. That turbid freshet of an Englishman, Wells, who did so much to stir his generation, said ‚ÄòI am wholly feminist‚Äô‚ÅÝ‚Äîand he was! He saw women only as females and wanted them endowed as such. He was never able to see them as human beings and amply competent to take care of themselves.

‚ÄúNow, our women, getting hold of this idea that they really are human creatures, simply blossomed forth in new efficiency. They specialized the food business‚ÅÝ‚ÄîHallie‚Äôs right about the importance of that‚ÅÝ‚Äîand then they specialized the baby business. All women who wish to, have babies; but if they wish to take care of them they must show a diploma.‚Äù

I looked at him. I didn‚Äôt like it‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut what difference did that make? I had died thirty years ago, it appeared.

‚ÄúA diploma for motherhood!‚Äù I repeated; but he corrected me.

‚ÄúNot at all. Any woman can be a mother‚ÅÝ‚Äîif she‚Äôs normal. I said she had to have a diploma as a child-culturist‚ÅÝ‚Äîquite a different matter.‚Äù

‚ÄúI don‚Äôt see the difference.‚Äù

‚ÄúNo, I suppose not. I didn‚Äôt, once,‚Äù he said. ‚ÄúAny and every mother was supposed to be competent to ‚Äòraise‚Äô children‚ÅÝ‚Äîand look at the kind of people we raised! You see, we are beginning to learn‚ÅÝ‚Äîjust beginning. You needn‚Äôt imagine that we are in a state of perfection‚ÅÝ‚Äîthere are more new projects up for discussion than ever before. We‚Äôve only made a start. The consequences, so far, are so good that we are boiling over with propositions for future steps.‚Äù

‚ÄúGo on about the women,‚Äù I said. ‚ÄúI want to know the worst and become resigned.‚Äù

‚ÄúThere‚Äôs nothing very bad to tell,‚Äù he continued cheerfully. ‚ÄúWhen a girl is born she is treated in all ways as if she was a boy; there is no hint made in any distinction between them except in the perfectly open physiological instruction as to their future duties. Children, young humans, grow up under precisely the same conditions. I speak, of course, of the most advanced people‚ÅÝ‚Äîthere are still backward places‚ÅÝ‚Äîthere‚Äôs plenty to do yet.

‚ÄúThen the growing girls are taught of their place and power as mothers‚ÅÝ‚Äîand they have tremendously high ideals. That‚Äôs what has done so much to raise the standard in men. It came hard, but it worked.‚Äù

I raised my head with keen interest, remarking, ‚ÄúI‚Äôve glimpsed a sort of ‚Äòiron hand in a velvet glove‚Äô back of all this. What did they do?‚Äù

Owen looked rather grim for a moment.

‚ÄúThe worst of it was twenty or twenty-five years back. Most of those men are dead. That new religious movement stirred the socio-ethical sense to sudden power; it coincided with the women‚Äôs political movement, urging measures for social improvement; its enormous spread, both by preaching and literature, lit up the whole community with new facts, ideas and feelings. Health‚ÅÝ‚Äîphysical purity‚ÅÝ‚Äîwas made a practical ideal. The young women learned the proportion of men with syphilis and gonorrhea and decided it was wrong to marry them. That was enough. They passed laws in every State requiring a clean bill of health with every marriage license. Diseased men had to die bachelors‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat‚Äôs all.‚Äù

‚ÄúAnd did men submit to legislation like that?‚Äù I protested.

‚ÄúWhy not? It was so patently for the protection of the race‚ÅÝ‚Äîof the family‚ÅÝ‚Äîof the women and children. Women were solid for it, of course‚ÅÝ‚Äîand all the best men with them. To oppose it was almost a confession of guilt and injured a man‚Äôs chances of marriage.‚Äù

‚ÄúIt used to be said that any man could find a woman to marry him,‚Äù I murmured, meditatively.

‚ÄúMaybe he could‚ÅÝ‚Äîonce. He certainly cannot now. A man who has one of those diseases is so reported‚ÅÝ‚Äîjust like small-pox, you see. Moreover, it is registered against him by the Department of Eugenics‚ÅÝ‚Äîphysicians are required to send in lists; any girl can find out.‚Äù

‚ÄúIt must have left a large proportion of unmarried women.‚Äù

‚ÄúIt did, at first. And that very thing was of great value to the world. They were wise, conscientious, strong women, you see, and they poured all their tremendous force into social service. Lots of them went into child culture‚ÅÝ‚Äîused their mother-power that way. It wasn‚Äôt easy for them; it wasn‚Äôt easy for the left-over men, either!‚Äù

‚ÄúIt must have increased prostitution to an awful extent,‚Äù I said.

Owen shook his head and regarded me quizzically.

‚ÄúThat is the worst of it,‚Äù he said. ‚ÄúThere isn‚Äôt any.‚Äù

I sat up. I stood up. I walked up and down. ‚ÄúNo prostitution! I‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI can‚Äôt believe it. Why, prostitution is a social necessity, as old as Nineveh!‚Äù

Owen laughed outright. ‚ÄúToo late, old man; too late! I know we used to think so. We did use to call it a ‚Äòsocial necessity,‚Äô didn‚Äôt we? Come, now, tell me what necessity it was to the women.‚Äù

I stopped my march and looked at him.

‚ÄúTo the women,‚Äù he repeated. ‚ÄúWhat did they want of prostitution? What good did it do them?‚Äù

‚ÄúWhy‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhy‚ÅÝ‚Äîthey made a living at it,‚Äù I replied, rather lamely.

‚ÄúYes, a nice, honorable, pleasant, healthy living, didn‚Äôt they? With all women perfectly well able to earn an excellent living decently; with all women fully educated about these matters and knowing what a horrible death was before them in this business; with all women brought up like human beings and not like over-sexed female animals, and with all women quite free to marry if they wished to‚ÅÝ‚Äîhow many, do you think, would choose that kind of business?

‚ÄúWe never waited for them to choose it, remember! We fooled them and lied to them and dragged them in‚ÅÝ‚Äîand drove them in‚ÅÝ‚Äîforced them in‚ÅÝ‚Äîand kept them as slaves and prisoners. They didn‚Äôt really enjoy the life; you know that. Why should they go into it if they do not have to‚ÅÝ‚Äîto accommodate us?‚Äù

‚ÄúDo you mean to tell me there are no‚ÅÝ‚Äîwantons‚ÅÝ‚Äîamong women?‚Äù I demanded.

‚ÄúNo, I don‚Äôt mean any such thing. There are various kinds of over-developed and morbidly developed women as there are men, and we haven‚Äôt weeded them out entirely. But the whole thing is now recognized as pathological‚ÅÝ‚Äîcases for medical treatment, or perhaps surgical. Besides, wantonness is not prostitution. Prostitution is a social crime of the worst order. No one thing did more harm. The women stamped it out.‚Äù

‚ÄúLegislated us all into morality, did they?‚Äù I inquired sarcastically.

‚ÄúLegislation did a good deal; education did more; the new religion did most; social opinion helped. You remember we men never really tried to legislate against prostitution‚ÅÝ‚Äîwe wanted it to go on.‚Äù

‚ÄúWhy, surely we did legislate against it‚ÅÝ‚Äîand it was of no use!‚Äù I protested.

‚ÄúNo; we legislated against the women, but not against the men, or the thing itself. We examined the women, and fined them, and licensed them‚ÅÝ‚Äîand never did anything against the men. Women legislators used very different measures, I assure you.‚Äù

‚ÄúI suppose it is for the good of the world,‚Äù I presently admitted; ‚Äúbut‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúBut you don‚Äôt quite like to think of men in this new and peculiar position of having to be good!‚Äù

‚ÄúFrankly‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI don‚Äôt. I‚Äôm willing to be good, but‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI don‚Äôt like to be given no choice.‚Äù

‚ÄúWell, now, look at it. As it was, we had one way, according to what we thought was good for us. Rather than lead clean, contented lives at some expense to ourselves in the way of moral and physical control, we deliberately sacrificed an army of women to a horrible life and a more horrible death, and corrupted the blood of the nation. It was on the line of health they made their stand, not on ‚Äòmorality‚Äô alone. Under our new laws it is held a crime to poison another human being with syphilis, just as much as to use prussic acid.‚Äù

‚ÄúNellie said you had no crime now.‚Äù

‚ÄúOh, well, Nellie is an optimist. I suppose she meant the old kinds and definitions. We don‚Äôt call things ‚Äòcrimes‚Äô any more. And then, really, there is not a hundredth part of the evil done that there used to be. We know more, you see, and have less temptation.‚Äù

We were silent for a while. I watched a gull float and wheel over the blue water. Big airships flew steadily along certain lines. Little ones sailed about on all sides.

One darted over our heads and lit with a soft swoop on an open promontory.

‚ÄúDidn‚Äôt they use to buzz?‚Äù I asked Owen.

‚ÄúOf course; just as the first motor boats thumped and banged abominably. We will not stand for unnecessary noise, as we used to.‚Äù

‚ÄúHow do you stop it? More interference with the individual rights?‚Äù

‚ÄúMore recognition of public rights. A bad noise is a nuisance, like a bad smell. We didn‚Äôt used to mind it much‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut the women did. You see, what women like has to be considered now.‚Äù

‚ÄúIt always was considered!‚Äù I broke in with some heat. ‚ÄúThe women of America were the most spoiled, pampered lot on earth; men gave up to them in all ways.‚Äù

‚ÄúAt home, perhaps, but not in public. The city and state weren‚Äôt run to suit them at all.‚Äù

‚ÄúWhy should they be? Women belong at home. If they push into a man‚Äôs world they ought to take the consequences.‚Äù

Owen stretched his long legs and looked up at the soft, brilliant blue above us.

‚ÄúWhy do you call the world ‚Äòman‚Äôs?‚Äù he asked.

‚ÄúIt was man‚Äôs; it ought to be. Woman‚Äôs place is in the home. I suppose I sound like ancient history to you?‚Äù and I laughed a little shamefacedly.

‚ÄúWe have rather lost that point of view,‚Äù Owen guardedly admitted. ‚ÄúYou see‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù and then he laughed. ‚ÄúIt‚Äôs no use, John; no matter how we put it to you it‚Äôs a jar. The world‚Äôs thought has changed‚ÅÝ‚Äîand you have got to catch up!‚Äù

‚ÄúSuppose I refuse? Suppose I really am unable?‚Äù

‚ÄúWe won‚Äôt suppose it for a moment,‚Äù he said cheerfully. ‚ÄúIdeas are not nailed down. Just take out what you had and insert some new ones. Women are people‚ÅÝ‚Äîjust as much as we are; that‚Äôs a fact, my dear fellow. You‚Äôll have to accept it.‚Äù

‚ÄúAnd are men allowed to be people, too?‚Äù I asked gloomily.

‚ÄúWhy, of course! Nothing has interfered with our position as human beings; it is only our sex supremacy that we have lost.‚Äù

‚ÄúAnd do you like it?‚Äù I demanded.

‚ÄúSome men made a good deal of fuss at first‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe old-fashioned kind, and all the worst varieties. But modern men aren‚Äôt worried in the least over their position.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ See here, John, you don‚Äôt grasp this‚ÅÝ‚Äîwomen are vastly more agreeable than they used to be.‚Äù

I looked at him in amazement.

‚ÄúFact!‚Äù he said. ‚ÄúOf course, we loved our own mothers and daughters and sisters, more or less, no matter how they looked or what they did; and when we were ‚Äòin love‚Äô there was no limit to the glory of ‚Äòthe beloved object.‚Äô But you and I know that women were pretty unsatisfactory in the old days.‚Äù

I refused to admit it, but he went on calmly.

‚ÄúThe ‚Äòwife and mother‚Äô was generally a tired, nervous, overworked creature. She soon lost her beauty and vigor, her charm and inspiration. We were forever chasing fine, handsome, highly desirable young girls, and forever reducing them to weary, worn-out women‚ÅÝ‚Äîin the name of love! The gay outsiders were always a fresh attraction‚ÅÝ‚Äîas long as we couldn‚Äôt have them.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ See here, John, can‚Äôt you understand? Our old way of using women wasn‚Äôt good for them‚ÅÝ‚Äînor for us, either, by the way‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut it simply spoiled the women. They were hopelessly out of the running with us in all human lines; their business was housework, and ours was world work. There was very little real companionship.

‚ÄúNow women are intelligent, experienced, well-trained citizens, fully our equals in any line of work they take up, and with us everywhere. It‚Äôs made the world over!‚Äù

‚ÄúMade it ‚Äòfeminist‚Äô through and through, I suppose!‚Äù I groaned.

‚ÄúNot a bit! It used to be ‚Äòmasculist‚Äô through and through; now it‚Äôs just human. And, see here‚ÅÝ‚Äîwomen are more attractive, as women, than they used to be.‚Äù

I stared at this, unbelieving.

‚ÄúThat‚Äôs true! You see, they are healthy; there‚Äôs a new standard of physical beauty‚ÅÝ‚Äîvery Greek‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou must have noticed already the big, vigorous, fresh-colored, free-stepping girls.‚Äù

I had, even in my brief hours of observation.

‚ÄúThey are far more perfect physically, better developed mentally, with a higher moral sense‚ÅÝ‚Äîyes, you needn‚Äôt look like that! We used to call them our ‚Äòmoral superiors,‚Äô just because they had the one virtue we insisted on‚ÅÝ‚Äîand we never noticed the lack in other lines. Women to-day are truthful, brave, honest, generous, self-controlled; they are‚ÅÝ‚Äîjollier, more reasonable, more companionable.‚Äù

‚ÄúWell, I‚Äôm glad to hear that,‚Äù I rather grudgingly admitted. ‚ÄúI was afraid they would have lost all‚ÅÝ‚Äîcharm.‚Äù

‚ÄúYes, we used to feel that way, I remember. Funny! We were convinced on the one hand that there was nothing to a woman but her eternal womanliness, and on the other we were desperately afraid her womanliness would disappear the moment she turned her mind to anything else. I assure you that men love women, in general and in particular, much more than they used to.‚Äù

I pondered. ‚ÄúBut‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhat sort of home life do you have?‚Äù

‚ÄúThink for a moment of what we used to have‚ÅÝ‚Äîeven in a ‚Äòhappy home.‚Äô The man had the whole responsibility of keeping it up‚ÅÝ‚Äîhis business life and interests all foreign to her. She had the whole labor of running it‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe direct manual labor in the great majority of cases‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe management in any case. They were strangers in an industrial sense.

‚ÄúWhen he came home he had to drop all his line of thought‚ÅÝ‚Äîand she hers, except that she generally unloaded on him the burden of inadequacy in housekeeping. Sometimes he unloaded, too. They could sympathize and condole, but neither could help the other.

‚ÄúThe whole thing cost like sin, too. It was a living nightmare to lots of men‚ÅÝ‚Äîand women! The only things they had in common were their children and ‚Äòsocial interests.‚Äô

‚ÄúWell‚ÅÝ‚Äînowadays, in the first place every body is easy about money. (I‚Äôll go into that later.) No woman marries except for love‚ÅÝ‚Äîand good judgment, too; all women are more desirable‚ÅÝ‚Äîmore men want to marry them‚ÅÝ‚Äîand that improves the men! You see, a man naturally cares more for women than for anything else in life‚ÅÝ‚Äîand they know it! It‚Äôs the handle they lift by. That‚Äôs what has eliminated tobacco.‚Äù

‚ÄúDo you mean to say that these women have arbitrarily prevented smoking?‚Äù I do not smoke myself, but I was angry nevertheless.

‚ÄúNot a bit of it, John‚ÅÝ‚Äînot a bit of it. Anybody can smoke who wants to.‚Äù

‚ÄúThen why don‚Äôt they?‚Äù

‚ÄúBecause women do not like it.‚Äù

‚ÄúWhat has that to do with it? Can‚Äôt a man do what he wants to‚ÅÝ‚Äîeven if they don‚Äôt like it?‚Äù

‚ÄúYes, he can; but it costs too much. Men like tobacco, but they like love better, old man.‚Äù

‚ÄúIs it one of your legal requirements for marriage?‚Äù

‚ÄúNo, not legal; but women disapprove of tobacco-y lovers, husbands, fathers; they know that the excessive use of it is injurious, and won‚Äôt marry a heavy smoker. But the main point is that they simply don‚Äôt like the smell of the stuff, or of the man who uses it‚ÅÝ‚Äîmost women, that is.‚Äù

‚ÄúBut what difference does it make? I dare say that most women did not like it before, but surely a man has a right‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúTo make himself a disgusting object to his wife,‚Äù Owen interrupted. ‚ÄúYes, he has a ‚Äòright‚Äô to. We would have a right to bang on a tin pan, I suppose‚ÅÝ‚Äîor to burn rubber, but he wouldn‚Äôt be popular!‚Äù

‚ÄúIt‚Äôs tyranny!‚Äù I protested.

‚ÄúNot at all,‚Äù he said, imperturbably. ‚ÄúWe had no idea what a nuisance we used to be, that‚Äôs all; or how much women put up with that they did not like at all. I asked a woman once‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhen I was a bachelor‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhy she objected to tobacco, and she frankly replied that a man who did not smoke was much pleasanter to kiss! She was a very fascinating little widow‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI confess it made me think.‚Äù

‚ÄúIt‚Äôs the same with liquor, I suppose? Let‚Äôs get it all told.‚Äù

‚ÄúYes, only more so. Alcoholism was a race evil of the worst sort. I cannot imagine how we put up with it so long.‚Äù

‚ÄúIs this spotless world of yours one solid temperance union?‚Äù

‚ÄúPractically. We use some light wines and a little spirits yet, but infrequently‚ÅÝ‚Äîin this country, at least, and Europe is vastly improved.

‚ÄúBut that was a much more serious thing than the other. It wasn‚Äôt a mere matter of not marrying! They used all kinds of means. But come on‚ÅÝ‚Äîwe‚Äôll be late to dinner; and dinner, at least, is still a joy, Brother John.‚Äù

XI

Dr. Borderson, it seemed, held the chair in Ethics at the University. I knew a Borderson once and was very fond of him. Poor Frank! If he was alive he would have more likely reached a prison or a hospital than a professorship. Yet he was brilliant enough. We were great friends in college, and before; let me see—thirty-five years ago. But he was expelled for improper conduct, and went from bad to worse. The last I had heard of him was in a criminal case—but he had run away and disappeared. I well remembered the grief and shame it was to me at the time to see such a promising young life ruined and lost so early.

Thinking of this, I was shown into the study of the great teacher of ethics, and as I shook hands I met the keen brown eyes of—Frank Borderson. He had both my hands and shook them warmly.

“Well, John! It is good to see you again. How well you look; how little you have changed! It’s a good world you’ve come back to, isn’t it?”

“You are the most astonishing thing I’ve seen so far,” I replied. “Do you really mean it? Are you—a Professor of Ethics?”

“When I used to be a God-forsaken rascal, eh? Yes, it’s really so. I’ve taught Ethics for twenty years, and gradually pushed along to this position. And I was a good deal farther off than Tibet, old man.”

I was tremendously glad to see him. It was more like a touch of the old life than anything I had yet found—except Nellie, of course. We spoke for some time of those years of boyhood; of the good times we had had together; of our common friends.

He kept me to dinner; introduced me to his wife, a woman with a rather sad, sweet face, which seemed to bear marks of deep experience; and we settled down for an evening’s talk.

“I think you have come to the right person, John; not only because of my special studies, but because of my special line of growth. If I can tell you what changed me, so quickly and so wholly, you won’t be much puzzled about the others, eh?”

I fully agreed with him. The boy I knew was clever enough to dismiss all theology, to juggle with philosophy and pick ethics to pieces; but his best friends had been reluctantly compelled to admit that he had “no moral character.” He had, to my knowledge, committed a number of unquestionable “sins,” and by hearsay I knew of vices and crimes that followed. And he was Dr. Borderson!

“I’ll take myself as a sample, Whitman fashion,” said he. “There I was when you knew me—conceited, ignorant, clever, self-indulgent, weak, sensual, dishonest. After I was turned out of college I broke a good many laws and nearly all the commandments. What was worse, in one way, was that my ‘wages’ were being paid me in disease—abominable disease. Also I had two drug habits—alchohol and cocaine. Will you take me as a sample?”

I looked at him. He had not the perfect health I saw so much of in the younger people; but he seemed in no way an invalid, much less a drug victim. His eyes were clear and bright, his complexion good, his hand steady, his manner assured and calm.

“Frank,” said I, “you beat anything I’ve seen yet. You stand absolutely to my mind as an illustration of ‘Before Taking’ and ‘After Taking.’ Now in the name of reason tell me what it was you Took!”

“I took a new grip on Life—that’s the whole answer. But you want to know the steps, and I’ll tell you. The new stage of ethical perception we are in now—or, as you would probably say, this new religion—presents itself to me in this way:

“The business of the universe about us consists in the Transmission of Energy. Some of it is temporarily and partially arrested in material compositions; some is more actively expressed in vegetable and animal form; this stage of expression we call Life. We ourselves, the human animals, were specially adapted for high efficiency in storing and transmitting this energy; and so were able to enter into a combination still more efficient; that is, into social relations. Humanity, man in social relation, is the best expression of the Energy that we know. This Energy is what the human mind has been conscious of ever since it was conscious at all; and calls God. The relation between this God and this Humanity is in reality a very simple one. In common with all other life forms, the human being must express itself in normal functioning. Because of its special faculty of consciousness, this human engine can feel, see, think, about the power within it; and can use it more fully and wisely. All it has to learn is the right expression of its degree of life-force, of Social Energy.” He beamed at me. “I think it’s about all there, John.”

“You may be a very good Professor of Ethics for these new-made minds, but you don’t reach the old kind—not a little bit. To my mind you haven’t said anything—yet.”

He seemed a little disappointed, but took it mildly. “Perhaps I am a little out of touch. Wait a moment—let me go back and try to take up the old attitude.”

He leaned back in his chair and shut his eyes. I saw an expression of pain slowly grow and deepen on his face; and suddenly realized what he was doing.

“Oh, never mind, Frank; don’t do it; don’t try. I’ll catch on somehow.”

He seemed not to hear me; but dropped his face in his hands. When he raised it was clear again. “Now I can make things clearer perhaps,” he said. “We had in our minds thirty years ago a strange hodge-podge of old and new ideas. What was called God was still largely patterned after the old tribal deity of the Hebrews. Our ideas of ‘Sin’ were still mostly of the nature of disobedience—wrong only because we were told not to do it. Sin as a personal offense against Somebody, and Somebody very much offended; that was it. We were beginning to see something of Social values, too, but not clearly. Our progress was in what we called ‘The natural sciences’; and we did not think with the part of our minds wherein we stored religion. Yet there was very great activity and progress in religious thought; the whole field was in motion; the new churches widening and growing in every direction; the older ones holding on like grim death, trying not to change, and changing in spite of themselves; and Ethics being taught indeed, but with no satisfying basis. That’s the kind of atmosphere you and I grew up in, John. Now here was I, an ill-assorted team of impulses and characteristics, prejudiced against religion, ignorant of real ethics, and generally going to the devil—as we used to call it! You know how far down I went—or something of it.”

“Don’t speak of it, Frank!” I said. “That was long ago; forget it, old man!” But he turned toward me a smile of triumph.

“Forget it! I wouldn’t forget one step of it if I could! Why, John, it’s because of my intimate knowledge of these down-going steps that I can help other people up them!”

“You looked decidedly miserable just now, all the same, when you were thinking them over.”

“Oh, bless you, John, I wasn’t thinking of myself at all! I was thinking of the awful state of mind the world was in, and how it suffered! Of all the horror and misery and shame; all that misplaced, unnecessary cruelty we called punishment; the Dark Ages we were still in, in spite of all we had to boast of. However, this new perception came.”

I interrupted him.

“What came? Who came? Did you have a new revelation? Who did it? What do you call it? Nobody seems to be able to give me definite information.”

He smiled broadly. “You’re a beautiful proof of the kind of mental jumble I spoke of. Knowledge of evolution did not come by a revelation, did it? Or did any one man, or two, give it to us? Darwin and Wallace were not the only minds that helped to see and express that great idea; and many more had to spread it. These great truths break into the world-mind through various individuals, and coalesce so that we cannot disconnect them. We have had many writers, preachers, lecturers, who discoursed and explained; this new precept as to the relation between man and God came with such a general sweep that no one even tries to give personal credit for it. These things are not personal—they are world-percepts.”

“But every religion has had its Founder, hasn’t it?”

“I don’t call it a religion, my dear fellow! It’s a science, like any other science. Ethics is The Science of Human Relation. It is called Applied Sociology—that’s all.”

“How does a thing like that touch one, personally?” I asked.

“How does any science touch one personally? One studies a science, one teaches a science, one uses a science. That’s the point—the use of it. Our old scheme of religion was a thing to ‘believe,’ or ‘deny’; it was a sort of shibboleth, a test question one had to pass examination in to get good marks! What I’m telling you about is a general recognition of right behavior, and a general grasp of the necessary power.”

“You leave out entirely the emotional side of religion.”

“Do I? I did not intend to. You see, we do not distinguish religion from life now, and are apt to forget old terms. You are thinking, I suppose, of the love of God, and man, which we used to preach. We practice it now.

“That Energy I spoke of, when perceived by us, is called Love. Love, the real thing we had in mind when we said ‘God is Love,’ is beneficent energy. It is the impulse of service, the desire to do, to help, to make, to benefit. That is the ‘love’ we were told to bestow on one another. Now we do.”

“Yes; but what made you do it? What keeps you up to it?”

“Just nature, John. It is human nature. We used to believe otherwise.” He was quiet for a while.

“One of these new doctors got hold of me, when I was about as near the bottom as one can go and get back. Not a priest with a formula, nor a reformer with an exhortation; but a real physician, a soul-doctor, with a passionate enthusiasm for an interesting case. That’s what I was, John; not a lost soul; not even a ‘sinner’—just ‘a case.’ Have you heard about these moral sanitariums?”

“Yes—but not definitely.”

“Well, as soon as this view of things took hold, they began to want to isolate bad cases, and cure them if they could. And they cured me.”

“How, Frank—how? What did they tell you that you didn’t know before? What did they do to you?”

“Sane, strong, intelligent minds put themselves in connection with mine, John, and shared their strength with me. I was made to feel that my individual failure was no great matter, but that my social duty was; that the whole of my dirty past was as nothing to all our splendid future, that whatever I had done was merely to be forgotten—the sooner the better, and that all life was open before me—all human life; endless, beautiful, profoundly interesting—the game was on, and I was in it.

“John—I wish I could make you feel it. It was as if we had all along had inside us an enormous reservoir of love, human love, that had somehow been held in and soured! This new arrangement of our minds let it out—to our limitless relief and joy. No ‘sin’—think of that! Just let it sink in. No such thing as sin. … We had, collectively and privately, made mistakes, and done the wrong thing, often. What of it? Of course we had. A growing race grew that way.

“Now we are wiser and need not keep on going wrong. We had learned that life was far easier, pleasanter, more richly satisfying when followed on these new lines—and the new lines were not hard to learn. Love was the natural element of social life. Love meant service, service meant doing one’s special work well, and doing it for the persons served—of course!

“All our mistakes lay in our belated Individualism. You cannot predicate Ethics of individuals; you cannot fulfill any religion as individuals. My fellow creatures took hold of me, you see. That power that was being used so extensively for physical healing in our young days had become a matter of common knowledge—and use.”

“How many of these—moral hygienists—did you have?”

“Scores, hundreds, thousands—we all help one another now. If a person is tired and blue and has lost his grip, if he can’t rectify it by change of diet and change of scene, he goes to a moral hygienist, as you rightly call it, and gets help. I do a lot of that sort of work.”

I meditated awhile, and again shook my head. “I’m afraid it’s no use. I can’t make it seem credible. I hear what you say and I see what you’ve done—but I do not get any clear understanding of the process. With people as they were, with all those casehardened old sinners, all the crass ignorance, the stupidity, the sodden prejudice, the apathy, the selfishness—to make a world like that see reason—in thirty years!—No—I don’t get it.”

“You are wrong in your premises, John. Human nature is, and was, just as good as the rest of nature. Two things kept us back—wrong conditions, and wrong ideas; we have changed both. I think you forget the sweeping advance in material conditions and its effect on character. What made the well-bred, well-educated, well-meaning, pleasant people we used to know? Good conditions, for them and their ancestors. There were just as pleasant people among the poor and among their millions of children; they had every capacity for noble growth—given the chance. It took no wholesale change of heart to make people want shorter hours, better pay, better housing, food, clothes, amusements. As soon as the shameful pressure of poverty was taken off humanity it rose like a freed spring. Humanity’s all right.”

“There were some things all wrong,” I replied, “that I know. You could not obliterate hereditary disease in ten—or thirty years. You couldn’t make clean women of hundreds of thousands of prostitutes. You couldn’t turn an invalid tramp into a healthy gentleman.”

He stopped me. “We could do better than that,” he said, “and we have. I begin to see your central difficulty, John; the difficulty that used to hold us all. You are looking at life as a personal affair—a matter of personal despair or salvation.”

“Of course, what else is it?”

“What else! Why, that is no part of human life! Human life is social, John, collectively, common, or it isn’t human life at all. Hereditary disease looks pretty hopeless when you see one generation or two or three so cursed. But when you realize how swiftly the stream of human life can be cleansed of it, you take a fresh hold. The percentage of hereditary disease has sunk by more than half in thirty years, John, and at its present rate of decrease will be gone, clean gone, in another twenty. Remember that every case is known, and that they are either prevented from transmitting the inheritance, isolated, or voluntarily living single. Diseases from bad conditions we no longer endure, nor diseases from ignorance, those from bacilli we are able to resist or cure; disease was never a permanent thing—only an accident. As for the prostitutes—we thought them ‘ruined’ because they were no longer suitable for our demands in marriage. As if that was everything! I tell you we opened a way out for them!”

“Namely?”

“Namely all the rest of life! Sex-life isn’t everything, John. Not fit to be a mother, we said to them; never mind—there is everything else in the world to be. You may remember, my friend, that thousands of men, as vicious as any prostitutes, and often as diseased, continued to live, to work, and to enjoy. Why shouldn’t the women? You haven’t ruined your lives, we said to them; only one part. It’s a loss, a great loss, but never mind, the whole range of human life remains open to you, the great moving world of service and growth and happiness. If you’re sick, you’re sick—we’ll cure it if possible. If not, you’ll die—never mind, we all die—that’s nothing.”

“Does your new religion call death nothing?”

“Certainly. The fuss we made about death was wholly owing to the old religions; the post-mortem religions, their whole basis was death.”

“Hold on a bit. Do you mean to tell me the people aren’t afraid of death any more?”

“Not a bit. Why should they be? Every living thing dies; that’s part of the living. We do not hide it from children now, we teach it to them.”

“Teach death—to children! How horrible!”

“Did you see or hear anything horrible in your educational excursions, John? I know you didn’t. No, they learn it naturally; in their gardens; in their autumn and winter songs; in their familiarity with insects and animals. Our children learn life, death, and immortality, from silk-worms; and, then only incidentally. The silk is what they are studying.

“It takes a great many silk-worms to make silk, generations of them. They see them born, live and die, as incidents in silk culture. So we show them how people are born, live and die, in the making of human history. The idea is worked into our new educational literature—and all our literature for that matter. We see human life as a continuous whole now. People are only temporary parts of it. Dying isn’t any more trouble than being born.

“People feared death, originally, because it hint; being chased and eaten was not pleasant. But natural dying does not hurt. Then they were made to fear it by the hell-school of religions. All that is gone by. Our religion rests on life.”

“The life of this world or the life eternal?”

“The eternal life of this world, John. We have no quarrel with anyone’s belief as to what may happen after death, that is a free field; but the glory and power of our religion is that it rests with assurance on common knowledge of the beautiful facts of life. Here is Humanity, a continuing stream of life. Its line of advance is clear. That which makes Humanity stronger, wiser and happier is evidently what is right for it to do. We do teach it to all our children.”

“And they do it?”

“Of course they do it. Why shouldn’t they?”

“But our evil tendencies—”

“We don’t have evil tendencies, John—and never did. We have earlier and later tendencies; and it is perfectly possible to show the child which is which.”

“But surely it is easier to follow the lower impulses than the higher; easier to give way than to strive.”

“There’s the old misconception, John, that ‘striving idea.’ We assumed that it was ‘natural’ to be ‘bad’ and ‘unnatural’ to be ‘good’—that we had to make special efforts, painful and laborious, to become better. We had not seen, thirty years ago, that social evolution is as ‘natural’ as the evolution of the horse from the eohippus. If it was easier to be an eohippus than a horse why did the thing change?

“As to that army of ‘fallen women’ you are so anxious about, they just got up again, that’s all, got up and went on. They had only fallen from one position; there was plenty of room left to stand and walk. Why they were not a speck on society compared to the ‘fallen men.’ Two hundred thousand prostitutes in the city of New York—well? How many patrons? A million, at the least. They kept on doing business, and enjoying life. I tell you, John, all the unnecessary evils of condition in the old days, were as nothing to the unnecessary evils of our foolish ideas! And ideas can be changed in the twinkling of an eye!

“As to your hoboes and bums, that invalid tramp you instanced—I can settle your mind on that point. I was an invalid tramp, John; a drunkard, a cocaine fiend, a criminal, sick, desperate, as bad as they make them.”

“Which brings us back to that ‘moral sanitarium’ I suppose?”

“Yes. I strayed away from it. I keep forgetting my own case. But it is an excellent one for illustration. I was taken hold of with the strong hand, and given a course of double treatment, deep and thorough. By double treatment I mean physical and mental at once; such a complete overhauling and wise care as enabled my exhausted vitality slowly to reassert itself, and at the same time such strong tender cheerful companionship, such well-devised entertainment, such interesting, irresistible instruction—Why, John—put a tramp into Paradise, and there’s some hope of him.”

I was about to say that tramps did not deserve Paradise, but as I remembered what this man had been, and saw what he was now, I refrained.

He read my mind at once.

“It’s not a question of desert, John. We no longer deal in terms of personal reward or punishment. If I have a bad finger or a bad tooth I save it if I can; not because it deserves it, but because I need it. People who used to be called sinners are now seen to be diseased members of society, and society turns all its regenerative forces on at once. We never used to dream of that flood of power we had at hand—the Regenerative Forces of Society!”

He sat smiling, his fine eyes full of light. “Sometimes we had to amputate,” he continued, “especially at first. It is very seldom necessary now.”

“You mean you killed the worst people?”

“We killed many hopeless degenerates, insane, idiots, and real perverts, after trying our best powers of cure. But it is really astonishing to see how much can be done with what we used to call criminals, merely by first-class physical treatment. I can remember how strange it seemed to me, having elaborate baths, massage, electric stimulus, perfect food, clean comfortable beds, beautiful clothes, books, music, congenial company, and wonderful instruction. It was very confusing. It went far to rearrange all my ideas.”

“If you treat—social invalids—like that, I should think they would ‘lie down;’ just to remain in hospital forever. Or go out and be bad in order to get back again.”

“Oh, no,” he said. “A healthy man can’t lie around and do nothing very long. Also it is good outside too, remember. Life is good, pleasant, easy. Why on earth should a man want to prowl around at night and steal when he can have all he wants, with less effort, in the daytime? Happy people do not become criminals.

“But I can tell you what treatment like that does to one. It gives a man a new view of human life, of what it is he belongs to. A sense of pride in our common accomplishment, of gratitude for the pleasure he receives, of a natural desire to contribute something. I took this new ethics—it satisfied me, it’s reasonable, it’s necessary. We make it our basic study now, in all the schools. You must have noticed that?”

Yes, I had noticed it, as I looked back. “But they don’t call it that,” I said.

“No, they don’t call it anything to the children. It is just life, the rules of decent behavior.”

We sat silent awhile after this. Things were clearing up a little in my mind.

“A sort of crystallization of chaotic progressive thought into clear diamonds of usable truth—is that about what happened?” I said.

“That’s exactly it.”

“And a general refutation and clearing out of—of.”

“Of a lot of things we deeply believed—that were not so! That is what was the matter with us, John. Our minds were full of what Mrs. Eddy christened error. I wish I could make you feel what a sunrise it was to the world when we left off believing lies and learned the facts.”

“Can you, in a few words, outline a little of your new ‘Ethics’ to the lay mind?”

“Easily. It is all ‘lay’ enough. We don’t make a separate profession of religion, or a separate science of ethics. Ethics is social hygiene—it teaches how humanity must live in order to be well and strong. We show the child the patent facts of social relation, how all our daily life, our accumulated wealth and beauty and continuing power, rests on common action, on what people do together. Everything about him teaches that. Then we show him the reasons why such and such actions are wrong, what the results are; how to avoid wrong lines of action and adopt right ones. It’s no more difficult than teaching any other game, and far more interesting.”

I suppose I looked unconvinced, for he added, “Remember we have nature on our side. It is natural for a social animal to develop social instincts; any personal desire which works against the social good is clearly a survival of a lower pre-social period; wrong, in that it is out of place. What we used to call criminals were relics of the past. By artificially maintaining low conditions, such as poverty, individual wealth, we bred low-grade types. We do not breed them any more.”

Again we sat silent. I was nursing my knee and sat looking into the fire; the soft shimmering play of rosy light and warmth with which electricity now gave jewels to our rooms.

He followed my eyes.

“That clean, safe, beautiful power was always here, John—but we had not learned of it. The power of wind and water and steam were here—before we learned to use them. All this splendid power of human life was here—only we did not know it.”

After that talk with Frank Borderson I felt a little clearer in my mind about what had taken place. I saw a good deal of him, and he introduced me to others who were in his line of work. Also I got to know his wife pretty well. She was not so great an authority on ethics as he; but an excellent teacher, widely useful.

One day I said something to her about her lovely spirit, and what she must have been to him—such an uplifting influence.

She laughed outright.

“I’ll have to tell you the facts, Mr. Robertson, as part of your instruction. So far from my uplifting him, he picked me out of the gutter, literally, dead drunk in the gutter, the lowest kind of wreck. He made me over. He gave me—Life.”

Her eyes shone.

“We work together,” she added cheerfully.

They did work together, and evidently knew much happiness. I noted a sort of deep close understanding between them, as in those who have been through the wars in company.

I found Nellie knew about them. “Yes, indeed,” she said. “They are devoted to each other, and most united in their work. He was just beginning to try to work, after his own rebuilding; but feeling pretty lonesome. He felt that he had no chance of any personal life, you see, and there were times when he missed it badly. He had no right to marry, of course; that is, with a well woman. And then he found this broken lily—and mended it. There can’t be any children, but there is great happiness, you can see that.”

“And they are—received?”

“Received?—Oh, I remember! You mean they are invited to dinners and parties. Why, yes.”

“Not among the best people, surely?”

“Precisely that, the very best; people who appreciate their wonderful lives.”

“Tell me this. Sister; what happened to the Four Hundred—the F.F. V’s—and the rest of the aristocracy?”

“The same thing that happened to all of us. They were only people, you see. Their atrophied social consciousness was electrified with the new thoughts and feelings. They woke up, too, most of them. Some just died out harmlessly. They were only by-products.”

I consulted a rather reactionary old professor of Sociology, Morris Banks; one who had been teaching Political Economy in my youth, and who ought to be able to remember things. I asked him if he would be so good as to show me the dark side of this shield.

“Surely there must have been opposition, misunderstanding, the usual difficulties of new adjustments,” I said. “You remember the first years of change—I wish you would give me a clear account of it.”

The old man considered awhile: “Take any one state, any city, or country locality, and study back a little,” he said, “and you find the story is about the same. There was opposition and dissent, of course, but it decreased very rapidly. You see the improvements at first introduced were such universal benefits that there could not be any serious complaint.

“By the time we had universal suffrage the women were more than ready for it, full of working plans to carry out, and rich by the experience of the first trials.

“By the time Socialism was generally adopted we had case after case of proven good in Socialistic methods; and also the instructive background of some failures.”

“But the big men who ran the country to suit themselves in my time, they didn’t give up without a struggle surely? You must have had some fighting,” I said.

He smiled in cheerful reminiscence. “We had a good deal of noise, if that’s what you mean. But there’s no fighting to be done, with soldiers, if the soldiers won’t fight. Our workingmen declined to shoot or to be shot any longer, and left the big capitalists to see what they could do alone.”

“But they had the capital?”

“Not all of it. The revenues of the cities and of the United States Government are pretty considerable, especially when you save the seventy per cent, we used to spend on wars past and possible; and the ten or twenty more that went in waste and graft. With a Socialist State private Capital has no grip!”

“Did you confiscate it?”

“Did not have to. The people who were worth anything, swung into line and went to work like other people. Those that weren’t were just let alone. Nobody has any respect for them now.”

“You achieved Socialism without bloodshed?”

“We did. It did not happen all at once, you see; just spread and spread and proved its usefulness.”